Yuto Watanabe

Born: 16 October 1999

Birthplace: Toyota city, Japan

Contact: ✓ yıwatanabe[at]ucsd.edu

in https://www.linkedin.com/in/yuto-watanabe-

7340ba27a/

Website: https://watanabeyuto.github.io



Personal Profile

I am a Ph.D. student at the ECE department, University of California San Diego, USA. I received the Bachelor's degree in Mechanical engineering and Master's degree in Informatics both from Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan, in 2022 and in 2024, respectively. I was fortunate to be advised by Prof. Kazunori Sakurama and Prof. Toshiyuki Ohtsuka. From April 2024 to August 2024, I was a research fellow at Kyoto University funded by the JSPS Research Fellowship for Young Scientist DC1. My research interests include control theory, optimization, and their applications to network systems (e.g., distributed algorithms). I was awarded the 2024 Funai Overseas Scholarship.

Education

Sept. 2024 – present	University of California San Diego Ph.D. student at the ECE department Advisor: Prof. Yang Zheng CA, U	SA
Apr. 2024 – Aug. 2024	Kyoto University	an
Apr. 2022 – Mar. 2024	Kyoto University Master of Informatics (GPA: 4.12/4.30) Thesis: Distributed optimization of clique-wise coupled problems via three-opera splitting	
Apr. 2018 – Mar. 2022	Kyoto University B.E. in Mechanical Engineering (GPA: 3.66/4.30) Thesis: Distributed dynamic matching of two groups of agents with different sense ranges	

Experiences

Oct. 2022 – Aug. 2024	Student Member of Advanced Mathematical Science for Mobility Society. The joint project of Kyoto University and Toyota Motor Corporation.
Apr. 2022 – Jul. 2022	Teaching Assistant at Kyoto University, Kyoto Japan. Teaching assistant of the Practice of Basic Informatics Class.
Mar. 2022 – Nov. 2022	Office Assistant at Kyoto University, Kyoto Japan. Translation of a monograph on multi-agent control into Japanese.

Research Publications

Journal Articles

[1] **Y. Watanabe**, K. Sakurama, and H.-S. Ahn, "Gradient-based distributed controller design over directed networks," *IEEE Transactions on Control of Network Systems*, 2024 (to appear).

Peer Reviewed International Conference Proceedings

- [1] **Y. Watanabe** and K. Sakurama, "Accelerated distributed projected gradient descent for convex optimization with clique-wise coupled constraints," in *the 22nd IFAC World Congress*, Yokohama, Japan, 2023.
- [2] **Y. Watanabe** and K. Sakurama, "Distributed optimization of clique-wise coupled problems," in *the* 62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), Singapore, 2023, pp. 296–302.
- [3] **Y. Watanabe** and K. Sakurama, "Distributed dynamic matching of two groups of agents with different sensing ranges," in *the 61st IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, Cancun, Mexico, 2022, pp. 5916–5921.

Papers in Preparation & Under Review

- [1] S. Fushimi, **Y. Watanabe**, and K. Sakurama, "Distributed controller design for discrete-time systems via the integration of extended lmi and clique-wise decomposition," submitted to *IEEE Control Systems Letters (ACC)* (under review).
- [2] **Y. Watanabe**, S. Fushimi, and K. Sakurama, "Characterization and convexification of LMI-based distributed controller design with a class of non-block-diagonal Lyapunov functions," submitted to *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control* (under review).
- [3] **Y. Watanabe** and K. Sakurama, "Distributed optimization of clique-wise coupled problems via three-operator splitting," submitted to *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control* (under review).

Awards

SCI Outstanding Student Presentation Award, SCI'24, Osaka, Japan.

SICE Outstanding Student Award, the Society of Instrument and Control Engineers (SICE). This award is given to the first-rank student recommended by each institution or department every year.

UC San Diego, ECE department fellowship.

2023 Funai Overseas Scholarship.

This scholarship will cover two years of graduate school tuition plus a stipend of 3,000USD a month for living expenses. (Only for the UK, it will cover three years.)

JSPS Research Fellowship for Young Scientist (Tokubetsu Kenkyuin) DC1.

A governmental three-year fellowship for Ph.D. students at Japanese institutions. The acceptance rate is around 14.3%.

IEEE CSS Student Travel & Workshop Support Programs of CDC 2023.

SCI Outstanding Student Presentation Award, SCI'23, Kyoto, Japan.

The 2023 ISCIE Young Investigators Award, The Institute of Systems, Control and Information Engineers, Japan.

This award is given to around five outstanding young researchers in the Japanese control community.

Skills

Languages English: IELTS (Academic) overall score: 7.5 (Jan 2024).

Japanese: Mother tongue.

Coding MATLAB, Python, and LaTeX.

Hobbies Running (my best time: 3:40:27 at Kyoto marathon 2023), juggling, training, etc.